Finding Aid for Collegiate Sorosis (University of Michigan) records 1886-1991
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Collegiate Sorosis (University of Michigan) records 1886-1991
Collegiate Sorosis (University of Michigan)
University of Michigan sorority, records include a history, minutes of meetings, records of Sorosis House, scrapbooks, printed matter, and photographs.
87107 BImu; Bimu F47 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
3 linear feet
1 oversize folders
The record group was the gift of different members of the organization (donor nos. 6359 and 8461
The records are open for research.
In 1886, the Michigan chapter of Kappa Alpha Theta, then one of the three secret societies for women at the University of Michigan, feeling dissatisfied with the limitations of a secret organization, resigned from the national society. A group of the former members immediately laid plans for the founding of a society that would have a broader social and educational influence. Contact was made with the New York Sorosis, a women's organization with many distinguished members, which had been founded in 1868. After a period of discussion, the Ann Arbor women received permission to found a college chapter of Sorosis at the U-M. The charter for this Collegiate Sorosis was granted on May 12, 1886.
Collegiate Sorosis was a University of Michigan sorority, supposedly the first on campus to build and have its own home. Its purpose was to "promote agreeable and useful relations among women of literary, artistic and scientific tastes, and to afford an opportunity for discussion among women of new facts and principles." (Collegiate Sorosis, History File) In this period before there were dormitories for women, before the establishment and building of the Michigan League, Collegiate Sorosis provided a place where its members could live within a nurturing environment.
With the decline of fraternity and sorority participation in the 1960s and 70s, and with the elimination of the university regulation that women students reside either in dorms or sororities until age 21, interest in Collegiate Sorosis dropped. In 1973, the alumnae of the chapter voted to disband and to sell the house. After a brief period, however, in 1978, some members of the Sorosis Club of Michigan expressed an interest in reviving (or recolonizing) Collegiate Sorosis. In 1980, ten members pledged to Sorosis and moved into a house on Cambridge Road. The sorority survives into the 1990s because of the energy and dedication of its alumnae.
The records of the Collegiate Sorosis document one of the oldest secret societies for women at the University of Michigan. The record group has been divided into five series: Minutes, Alphabetical, Finances, Photographs, and Scrapbooks.
Subjects:
University of Michigan--Students--Societies, etc.; Women--Michigan--Ann Arbor--Societies and clubs.; Greek letter societies--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women college students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects - Visual Material:
University of Michigan--Students--Societies, etc.; Women--Michigan--Ann Arbor--Societies and clubs.; Greek letter societies--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women college students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Minutes 1893-1991
  The Minutes series includes records for both the Collegiate Sorosis and for the Sorosis Club of Michigan. The minutes of Collegiate Sorosis date from 1893 to 1968 with two gaps in the 1920s and 1930s. The minutes of the Sorosis Club of Michigan date from 1950 to 1991 with a gaps from 1958 to 1963 and 1968 to 1986.
  - Alumnae Club-Collegiate Sorosis 1926-1947 (Box 1)
  - Collegiate Sorosis
    - November 1893-January 1903 (Box 1)
    - February 1903-June 1919 (Box 1)
    - April 1922-October 1925 (Box 1)
    - February 1932-October 1935 (Box 1)
    - October 1936-June 1941 (Box 1)
      (Secretary's Copy)
    - November 1935-April 1941 (Box 1)
    - October 1941-May 1949 (Box 1)
    - October 1949-May 1957 (Box 1)
    - May 1957-November 1964 (Box 1)
    - November 1964-April 1968 (Box 1)
  - President's Book 1947-February 1953 (Box 1)
  - Sorosis Club of Michigan
    - October 1950-March 1951 (Box 1)
    - June 1952-September 1958 (Box 1)
    - 1963-1967 (Box 1)
    - 1987-1988 (Box 1)
    - 1989-1991 (Box 1)
  - Triennial Convention (Box 1)
- Alpha Files 1892-1991
  The Alphabetical series consists of subject files as well as files of correspondence, historical information, rosters and directories, published material, and such governing documents as the constitution and bylaws and the house rules.
  - Chapter Rededication Ceremony 1987 (Box 2)
  - Chapter Rededication and New Initiation Ceremonies 1987-1991 (Box 2)
  - Clippings (Box 2)
  - Correspondence 1906-1989, undated
    - Alumnae
      - 1906, 1909, 1933, 1951, undated (Box 2)
      - 1965-1970, 1987-1989, undated (Box 2)
    - University 1922, 1927 (Box 2)
  - Governing Documents 1913-1990
    - Bylaws and Amendments Undated (Box 2)
    - Constitutions circa 1933, circa 1939, 1987 (Box 2)
      (see also "Printed Material--Yearbooks, 1892")
    - House Rules
      - circa 1990 (Box 2)
      - Undated (Box 2)
    - Reports 1913-1954, undated (Box 2)
    - Sorosis Club Board Undated (Box 2)
  - Histories 1986, 1988, undated (Box 2)
  - Printed Material 1892-1991
    - Initiation Ceremonies (Invitations) 1897, 1906-1966 (Box 2)
      (scattered)
    - Newsletters 1945-1971, 1984-1991, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Pledge Manual Undated (Box 2)
    - Songs Undated (Box 2)
    - Yearbooks 1892, 1915 (Box 2)
  - Rosters and Directories 1937-1991
    - Active Members and Recent Graduates 1967-1969, 1987-1990 (Box 2)
    - Ann Arbor Alumnae 1964-1967, 1988, undated (Box 2)
    - Alumnae Directory 1969 (Box 2)
    - New Member Signatures 1937-1972 (Box 2)
      (Bound Volume, also includes Initiation Ceremony and Scholarship Information)
    - Sorosis Club Boards of Directors
      - 1936-1952 (Box 2)
      - 1979-1991 (Box 2)
  - Scholarship Recipients (Box 2)
    (see "Rosters and Directories--New Member Signatures")
  - Student Government
    - Panhellenic Association 1936, 1962-1964 (Box 2)
    - Student Government Council 1962-1964, undated (Box 2)
- Finances 1896-1985
  The Finances series includes files pertaining to the fundraising for and construction of the Collegiate Sorosis house. There is also a record book of the House Committee dated from 1933 to 1947.
  - Construction and Fundraising 1896-1985, undated
    - 1896-1906, 1921-1928, 1938-1951 (Box 2)
    - 1960-1962, 1973, 1985 (Box 2)
    - Undated (Box 2)
  - House Committee 1933-1947 (Box 2)
    (Bound Volume)
  - Legal and Financial Documents 1923-1952, 1963-1969, undated (Box 2)
- Photographs 1886-1967
  The Photographs series consists of albums and loose photographs of Collegiate Sorosis members. Also included are photographs of the laying of the cornerstone at the Sorosis House in 1906 as well as other views of the house in the 1940s.
  - Albums
    - Candids, circa 1956-1957 (Box 2)
    - Portraits, circa 1938-1940 (Box 2)
  - Groups
    - 1886 (Folder UBImum/F47)
    - 1895 (Box 2)
    - 1897 (Folder UBImum/F47)
    - 1904 (Folder UBImum/F47)
    - 1910 (Box 2)
    - 1913 (Box 2)
    - circa 1916 (Folder UBImum/F47)
    - 1922 (Folder UBImum/F47)
    - 1956-1967 (Box 2)
  - Sorosis House (1501 Washtenaw Ave.)
    - Laying of Cornerstone 1906 (Folder UBImum/F47)
    - 1943-1944, undated (Box 2)
- Scrapbooks 1946-1966, 6 volumes
  Scrapbooks consist of clippings, programs, and other memorabilia of Collegiate Sorosis activities. They are dated 1946-1966.
  - 1946-1966, 6 volumes (Box 3)